<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>3 on Academic</title>
    <link>https://eric-roca.github.io/publication_types/3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 3 on Academic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; {year} Èric Roca Fernández</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://eric-roca.github.io/publication_types/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>In the Name of the Father: Inheritance Systems and the Dynamics of State Capacity</title>
      <link>https://eric-roca.github.io/working_papers/inheritance-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eric-roca.github.io/working_papers/inheritance-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;strong&gt;Accepted at &lt;em&gt;Macroeconomic Dynamics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;br&gt; This paper examines how the degree of gender-egalitarianism embedded in inheritance rules impacts state building. Male-biased inheritance rules historically maximise the likelihood of dynastic continuity. However, there is more land merging under gender-egalitarian rules. We compare both types of inheritance rules, concluding that, contrary to the literature, gender-egalitarian norms promote state capacity in the short run more than gender-biased norms. In the long run results are reversed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roots of Gender Equality: the Persistent Effect of Beguinages on Attitudes Toward Women</title>
      <link>https://eric-roca.github.io/working_papers/beguines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eric-roca.github.io/working_papers/beguines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;strong&gt;Awarded the &amp;lsquo;UWIN Best Paper Award on Gender Economics&amp;rsquo;, 7th edition.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Awarded a &amp;lsquo;Valeria Solesin&amp;rsquo; accessit, 2018 edition.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt; This paper is concerned with the historical roots of gender equality. It proposes and empirically assesses a new class of determinants of gender equality: increases in women&amp;rsquo;s bargaining power through reductions in the cost of remaining single. In particular, enlarging women&amp;rsquo;s options besides marriage &amp;mdash;even if only temporarily&amp;mdash; increases their bargaining power with respect to men, leading to a persistent improvement in gender equality. We illustrate this mechanism focusing on the specific Belgian context, and relate gender-equality levels in the 19th century to the presence of medieval, female-only communities called &lt;em&gt;beguinages&lt;/em&gt; that allowed women to remain single amidst a society that advocated the opposite. Combining precise beguinages&amp;rsquo; location with 19th-century census data, we document that beguinages were instrumental in decreasing the gender gap in literacy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>